Finding Aid for Muschenheim, William. Architectural drawings and papers. 1925-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Project Files
  - Job 39, Astor Hotel
    - [Hotel Astor (New York, N.Y.). Alterations. Remodeling]
      - Drawings, #.00618-.00747 1929-1937, 130 sheets: various media; or smaller 103 x 137 cm.; 40-1/2 x 54 inches
        - Bar and café: plan of alteration, September 27, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00705
          [88]
        - Bar and café: plan of alteration, September 27, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00706; Blueprint on paper.
          [89]
        - Alteration to bar: sketch plan with ceiling lay-out., NYDA.1986.004.00707
          [90]
        - Alt. to bar and café: ceil. plan, September 30th, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00708
          [91]
        - Alt. to bar and café: ceil. plan, September 30th, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00709; Blueprint on paper.
          [92]
        - Extension to bar: [study of plan showing some measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00710
          [93]
        - Extension to bar: plan [showing measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00711
          [94]
        - Bar: plan [with measurements], January 8th, [19]34., NYDA.1986.004.00712
          (Verso notes "Bar. Froehlich".)
          [95]
        - Bar: [plan showing extension with measurements] / Jacob Froehlich [of] Cabinet Works., NYDA.1986.004.00713
          [96]
        - Alteration to bar: elevations [showing west face and south face of bar]., NYDA.1986.004.00714
          [97]
        - Alteraton to bar: elevations [showing north, south, east and west sides with measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00715
          [98]
        - Bar in buffet restaurant: preliminary scheme [showing elevations "A", "B" and "C", and two sections], October 9t 1933., NYDA.1986.004.00716
          [99]
        - Bar extension: elevation of revised south side of south store lobby., NYDA.1986.004.00717
          [100]
        - [Bar extension (?): showing elevation of revised south side of south store lobby (?)]., NYDA.1986.004.00718
          [101]
        - New bar: elevations of alterations [showing elevations "A", and "C", and two sections]: File 212, Drawing 13 / Peabody Wilson and Brown, architects; drawn by W. M[uschenheim] 5/14/1934, NYDA.1986.004.00719
          (Verso notes "Job #212, #13, Elevations of alterations for new bar (cafe), scale 1/2" = 1'-0")
          [102]
        - New café: four elevations: File 212, Drawing 8 / Peabody Wilson and Brown, architects; drawn by W. M[uschenheim] 5/5/1934, NYDA.1986.004.00720
          (Verso notes "Café-Bar".)
          [103]
        - Cashier's booth: [three elevations, plan, and a plan of the back bar, with some measurements], February 9th, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00721
          [104]
        - [Broadway entrance (?): plan showing two revolving doors]., NYDA.1986.004.00722
          [105]
        - Astor Café: [plan of] revolving door B'way entrance]., NYDA.1986.004.00723
          (Taken from a letter to Muschenheim, from Peabody Wilson and Brown, signed by Albert Wilson dated 2/15/1935 The letter is located in Archival Folder 4 for Bills and Correspondence.)
          [106]
        - Astor Café: aluminum brackets [showing] isometric [i.e. axonometric] of coat hook bracket an F.S.D. side elevation of coat hook; aluminum door handles [showing] elev. of new door handles in reference to existing stiles, and F.S.D. sect. of new door handle on existing B'way door, October 10th, 1934., NYDA.1986.004.00724
          [107]
        - Detail of pull [and] push bar [showing elevation, section, and plan, with measurements]: Drawing no. 35-1 / C.E. Halback [and] Co.; made by A.P. 12/10/1934, NYDA.1986.004.00725
          [108]
        - Isometric [i.e. axonometric] sketch of show-window alteration in south store lobby, February 11, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00726
          [109]
        - [Bar: study for interior perspective]., NYDA.1986.004.00727
          [110]
        - [Bar: study for interior perspective showing curved corner and post]., NYDA.1986.004.00728
          [111]
        - [Bar: interior perspective showing curved end]., NYDA.1986.004.00729
          [112]
        - [Bar: interior perspective showing curved end]. Photostat on paper., NYDA.1986.004.00730
          (Verso notes "Bar-perspectives".)
          [113]
        - 45th St.: elevation [showing street level]., NYDA.1986.004.00731
          [114]
        - New ball room: [plan] / [drawn by] E.D.; [revised by (?)] F.W.B., December 30, [19]31, rev.(?) 9/14/1932, NYDA.1986.004.00732
          [115]
        - Belvedere roof garden: [plan showing lay-out] / F.W.B. 9/8/1933, NYDA.1986.004.00733
          (Verso notes "Belvedere".)
          [116]
        - Belvedere roof garden: [plan showing lay-out] / F.W.B., 9/8/[19]33, 7/51934 5/14/1935, NYDA.1986.004.00734
          (Verso notes "Roof Belvedere".)
          [117]
        - Alt. to Belvedere: ceiling plan: Drawing no. 1, February 10th, 1936., NYDA.1986.004.00735
          [118]
        - New ball room: north elevation., NYDA.1986.004.00736
          [119]
        - [New ball room (?): half of east elevation]., NYDA.1986.004.00737
          [120]
        - [Belvedere: interior perspective]., NYDA.1986.004.00738
          [121]
        - [Belvedere: interior perspective]., NYDA.1986.004.00739; Blueprint on paper.
          [122]
        - [Belvedere: interior perspective showing proposed alt. to portion of ceiling], June 12th, 1935., NYDA.1986.004.00740
          [123]
        - [Belvedere: interior perspective showing proposed alteration to portion of ceiling]., NYDA.1986.004.00741
          (Pastel and pencil on tracing paper; 42.5 x 60.1 cm. (16-6/8 x 23-5/8 in.))
          [124]
        - [Belvedere: interior perspective showing stairs]., NYDA.1986.004.00742
          (Pastel on tracing paper; 61.6 x 115.5 cm. (24-1/4 x 45-1/2 in.))
          [125]
        - [Belvedere: interior perspective showing skylights and french windows]., NYDA.1986.004.00743
          [126]
        - [Plant boxes: showing plan and south, east and west elevations with measurements] / F.W.B., 4-23-[19]32., NYDA.1986.004.00744
          [127]
        - Belvedere: north music platform and plant boxes [showing axonometric view with measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00745
          [128]
        - Belvedere: south music platform and plant boxes [showing axonometric view with measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00746
          [129]
        - [South garden entrance: elevations of east and south walls]., NYDA.1986.004.00747
          [130]
      - Papers
        - archival: specifications. (Box A3, Folder 39-1)
          (1 typed sheet titled "Memorandum specification for alterations in Flower Shop, Hotel Astor, NYC"; 1 carbon copy of document, 39 pp. titled, "Specification for Alterations in Ground Floor Assembly Rooms, Hotel Astor, New York, Wilson & Rahm Architects, Hotel Astor, Inc. Owner"; 1 carbon copy of document, 47 pp. titled, "Specification for Alterations in mezzanine & Lobby, Hotel Astor, NYC.")
        - archival: estimates (Box A3, Folder 39-2)
          (from C.E. Halbback & Co. (ornamental iron and bronze), Contempora Inc., Blanchard Bro. & Lane (tanners), Claude Meon Lights Inc.)
        - archival: orders (Box A3, Folder 39-3)
          (from Renaissance Meta Works, Thonet Brothers (furniture), Electro Sun Company Inc. (architects' supplies), Kurt Versen (lighting).)
        - archival: statements, correspondence. (Folder 39-4)
          (Corresponded with: Marshall Field & Company; Peabody, Wilson & Brown, Architects; Evelyn A. Pitshke (photographer); John Maxwell, Inc. (lighting fixtures); and C&H Construction Co. Statements sent to the attention of Mr. F.A. Muschenheim.)
        - drawings (4 sheets) & notes: correspondence. (Box A3, Folder 39-7)
          (1 letter from Machinery Builders, Inc.; 2 letters from The Walter M. Ballard Co. re the Fair Building Design Competition, and the ballroom; 1 small page of notes and pencil drawings.)
        - Ball Room, 1 sheets (Box A3, Folder 39-8)
          (3 paint samples)
        - 4 sheets & affidavit, 2 sheets (Box A3, Folder 39-9)
          (1 sample copy of affidavit, with 1 sample copy of altered buildings application, both written on.)
      - Photographs
        - Ballroom Old and New (Box B10)
        - Bar and Cafe (Box B10)
        - Belvedere and Open Roof (Box B10)
        - Carl and Linda's Rooms (Box B10)
        - Eighth Floor Coat Rooms (Box B10)
        - Exterior Views New (Box B10)
        - Exterior Views Old (Box B10)
        - Grill Room (Box B10)
        - Miscellaneous (Box B10)
        - Reception Rooms (Box B10)
        - Old Restaurant Lobby (Box B10)
      - Presentation Boards
        - Astor Cafe 1934 (Oversized) (Box B12)
        - Ball Room Lobby and Coat Room (0versized) 1935 (Box B12)
        - Lobby Leading to Restaurants and Roof Garden Alterations, Hotel Astor 1932-1938 (Box B7)
        - Banquet Hall Cafe and Ball Room Alterations, Hotel Astor 1934-1938 (Box B7)
        - Coat Room, Bar, Roof Restaurant, Hotel Astor 1934-1935 (Box B7)
        - Alteration to Cottage, Hampton Bays, L.I. 1934, 2 boards (Box B7)
  - Job 40, State of New York, Dept. of Health
    - [State of New York, Department of Health. Laboratory lunch room. Windows]
      - Drawings, #.00749-.00751 1934, 1935, 3 sheets: various media; or smaller 55.3 x 66.3 cm.; 21-3/4 x 26-1/8 inches
        This set consists of 1 pencil on tracing paper, 1 pencil on paper, and 1 pencil on brown paper
        - [Sketch of elevation of windows from dining room, with measurements] / J. Temple, 6/5/1934, NYDA.1986.004.00749
        - [Sketch of north and west interior elevations, and a section] / J. Temple 10/28/1935, NYDA.1986.004.00750
        - MYDA.1986.004.00751. Sketch of window treatment in laboratory lunchroom [showing elevation, plan, and section, with measurements]: Drawing no. 1, November 8th, 1935.
      - Papers
        - drawing 1: (Box A3, Folder 40-1)
          (1 sample of plywood)
        - archival: correspondence, invoice, notes, samples of curtain material, requisition, estimate. (Box A3, Folder 40-3)
          (Corresponded with: Miss Mary B. Kirkbride and others from the Department of Health.)
  - Job 41, District no. 5, Manhattan
    - [Slum Clearance Housing Proposal, District no. 5, Manhattan (New York, N.Y.). Urban renewal]
      - Drawings, .00752-.00800, .00995-.00996 1934, 1943, 51 sheets: various media; or smaller 90.6 x 104.5 cm.; 35-3/4 x 41-1/8 inches
        This set consists of 22 pencil on tracing paper, 2 pencil with pastel on tracing paper, 3 pencil with colored pencil on tracing paper, 8 stats on paper, 1 ink on paper, 2 blackline prints on linen, 1 blackline print on paper, 8 blueline prints on paper, 2 blueline prints with pastel on paper, and 2 brownprints on paper. This project was in response to a competition sponsored by the New York City Housing Authority, June 18, 1934. It was considered a "solution for the demolition and rebuilding of the slum area between 60th and 78th Streets and 2nd Avenue and the East River"--Architectural Record, March 1935
        - [Block plan of 60th to 79th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River showing buildings at 68th to 71st Streets and Avenue A and the East River]., NYDA.1986.004.00752
        - [Block plan of 58th to 79th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River showing selected buildings]., NYDA.1986.004.00753
          (Also shows doodle in pastel on the side.)
        - [Block plan of 60th to 78th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River showing selected existing buildings and possible development]., NYDA.1986.004.00754
        - [Block plan showing study for an intermediate scheme for redevelopment from 58th to 79th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River]., NYDA.1986.004.00755
        - [Site plan of 60th to 79th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River showing study of land values]., NYDA.1986.004.00756
          (Includes many computations.)
        - [Block plan of 59th to 78th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River showing land values at conditions prior to redevelopment], [1934]., NYDA.1986.004.00757
          (This sheet was part of the proposal of August 1934 and includes a typed legend.)
        - [Study for zoning plan for housing proposal showing block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment]., NYDA.1986.004.00758
        - Zoning plan for housing proposal [showing] district no. 5 [with a legend]., NYDA.1986.004.00759
        - Zoning plan for housing proposal [for] district no. 5 [with a legend]., NYDA.1986.004.00760; Blackline print on linen.
        - Zoning study, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment, with a legend], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00761
        - Zoning study, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment, with a legend], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00762
          (Blueline print on paper.)
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.00762]., NYDA.1986.004.00763
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.00762]., NYDA.1986.004.00764
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.00762]., NYDA.1986.004.00765
        - Zoning study, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment, with a legend], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00766
          (Blueline print with pastel on paper.)
        - [Reverse image of] Zoning study, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment, with a legend], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00767; Brownprint on paper.
        - Zoning study-S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment]., NYDA.1986.004.00768
        - Zoning study-S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan with existing buildings and proposed redevelopment]., NYDA.1986.004.00769; Stat in negative of 1986.004.00768.
        - Study of superblock lay-out, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00770
        - Study of superblock lay-out, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00771; Blueline print on paper.
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.00771]., NYDA.1986.004.00772
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.00771]., NYDA.1986.004.00773
        - [Duplicate copy of 1986.004.00771]., NYDA.1986.004.00774
        - Study of superblock lay-out, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00775; Blueline print with pastel on paper.
        - [Reverse image of] study of superblock lay-out, S.E. Yorkville area [showing a block plan], March 22, 1943., NYDA.1986.004.00778
        - Study of superblock lay-out housing proposal [showing block plan of 72nd to 78th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River]., NYDA.1986.004.00776
        - Study of superblock lay-out housing proposal [showing block plan of 72nd to 78th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River]., NYDA.1986.004.00777; Blackline print on linen.
        - Study of superblock lay-out; [and] zoning plan for housing proposal [both showing block plan for District no. 5, Manhattan]., NYDA.1986.004.00779
        - [Study of floor plans for apartments including corridor, stairwell and elevator shaft]., NYDA.1986.004.00780
          (Rooms are labeled and show measurements.)
        - [Floor plan of 2-1/2 room apartment from a 5-story walk-up, showing furnishings]., NYDA.1986.004.00781
        - [Floor plans of apartments from a 5-story walk-up, showing apartments with 1-1/2, 2-1/2, 3, 3-1/2, 4, 4-1/2 and 5 rooms, including measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00782
          (The apt. showing 5 rooms is crossed out.)
        - [Floor plans of apartments from a 5-story walk-up, showing apartments of 1-1/2, 2-1/2, 3, 3-1/2, 4, 4-1/2, and 5 rooms, including measurements]., NYDA.1986.004.00783
        - [Study of floor plans of apartments showing 4 schemes with stairs]., NYDA.1986.004.00784
        - [Typical floor plan showing the schemes found in 1986.004.00784]., NYDA.1986.004.00785
          (Heavily noted with square footage computations.)
        - [Floor plans of two apartments from a 12-story building with an elevator, showing terraces and furnishings in one apartment]., NYDA.1986.004.00786
        - [Study of floor plans of apartments from a 12-story elevator building, showing apartments with 5 rooms and 4 rooms]., NYDA.1986.004.00787
          (Heavily noted)
        - [Study of floor plans of apartments from a 12-story elevator building, showing apartments with 5 rooms and 4 rooms]., NYDA.1986.004.00789
          (Each apartment has 1 less closet than those in 1986.004.99787. Also includes a small sketch of a man's head in the lower left corner.)
        - [Floor plans and typical floor plan of apartments from a 12-story building with an elevator]., NYDA.1986.004.00790
          (Drawing is similar to 1986.004.00787 except the terrace is flush to the building.)
        - [Study of floor plans of apartments from a 12-story (?) building with an elevator, showing apartments with 5 and 3 rooms]., NYDA.1986.004.00791
          (Includes some notation.)
        - [Partial plan oblique of 12-story apartment building with an elevator, showing stairwell]., NYDA.1986.004.00792
        - [Axonometric view with a longitudinal section showing an elevator and stairwell of a distribution floor apartment building]., NYDA.1986.004.00793 R
        - [Trace of reverse image of 1986.004.00793R]., NYDA.1986.004.00793 V
        - [Bird's-eye view perspective of recreation area]., NYDA.1986.004.00794
          (Lower right corner is missing.)
        - [Bird's-eye view perspective of recreational area]., NYDA.1986.004.00795; Stat on paper.
        - [Block plan oblique of District no. 5, Manhattan]., NYDA.1986.004.00796
          (Upper right hand corner is missing.)
        - [Aerial view with block plan oblique of District no. 5, Manhattan], August 1934., NYDA.1986.004.00797
        - [Presentation board showing existing conditions, intermediate development and ultimate scheme drawings] August 1934, NYDA.1986.004.00798
          (Stat on paper.)
        - [Lettering for Slum Clearance Housing Proposal]., NYDA.1986.004.00799
        - [Sample of lettering for the Slum Clearance Housing Proposal]., NYDA.1986.004.00788
        - [Site plan showing north and south traffic, Queensboro Bridge Plaza, Second Avenue Tunnel, and York Avenue Extension] / Land Utilization Committee, N.Y. Building Congress, Robert Niles Jr.; [drawn by (?)] S. Hirst, November 1934., NYDA.1986.004.00800
          (Taken from letter to Morrison Brounn, from Robert Niles Jr., dated 4/29/1935 located in archival folder 1 of Drawings and Notes.)
        - [Block plan, 60th to 78th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River, showing land values]., NYDA.1986.004.00995
        - [Site plan, 61st to 79th Streets and 2nd Avenue to the East River, showing square footage and land values with computations]., NYDA.1986.004.00996
      - Papers
        - drawings & notes:, 2 items (Box A3, Folder 41-1)
          (clipping, notes, newspaper. 1 clipping re slum clearance; 5 pages of numerical notes; 1 copy of The City Record.)
        - drawings & notes:, 7 items (Box A3, Folder 41-2)
          (12 pages of handwritten computations (removed from envelope marked: "Muschenheim computations 1/17/40"); 5 pages of handwritten notes.)
        - drawings & note:, 20 items (Box A3, Folder 41-3)
          (1 program of competition for qualifications of architects, from the NYC Housing Authority)
        - archival: correspondence, notes, pamphlet, report, directory, clipping. (Box 4, Folder 41-5)
          (Correspondents include: Rosalie Manning from the Yorkville Planning & Housing Council, with related material.)
        - archival: leaflet correspondence, applications, fact sheets, minutes, clippings, address, pamphlet, notes. (Box A4, Folder 41-6)
          (Approx. 40 pages of printed material removed from envelope addressed to WM, from the NYC Housing Authority; 1 address by WM delivered at a meeting of The Yorkville Civic Council, (4 pp.); 15] pages of handwritten computations; and other related material.)
        - archival: photographs, report, proposal, clipping. (Box A4, Folder 41-7)
          (photographs (4 items) of models and other images related to the slum clearance housing proposal; 1 report of a study by the Works Progress Administration re Yorkville, (25 pp.); and other related material.)
        - Notes (Box A4, Folder 41-8)
          (Items in this folder were originally found separately rolled-roll V: 1 handwritten note stating-"Slum Clearance Housing Studies, Dist. no. 5, Manhattan"; with 5 pages of related material.)
        - archival: correspondence, notes, brochures, address, periodical, report, bulletin, pamphlet. (Box A4, Folder 41-9)
          (1 pamphlet and 3 brochures removed from an envelope addressed to WM, from the Department of the Interior, re housing; 1 address delivered by WM to the Yorkville Civic Council (with a duplicate copy); correspondence with the Federal Emergency Administration of Public Works, NYC Housing Authority, Treasury Dept., and others; and other material related to housing)
      - Photographs
        - "Unidentified Prints, Slides, Negatives (Box B11)
      - Presentation Boards
        - Slum Clearing House Proposal, 3 boards (Box B12)
  - Job 42, Portland Cement Co.
    - [Portland Cement Competition. Competition drawings]
      - Drawings, #.00801-.00820 1936, or smaller 62.2 x 61 cm.; 24-1/2 x 24 inches; 20 drawings pencil on tracing paper
        - [Sketch of first floor plan showing furniture lay-out]., NYDA.1986.004.00801
        - [First floor plan showing lay-out]., NYDA.1986.004.00802
        - [Partial plan sketch of living room and part of dining room]., NYDA.1986.004.00803
        - [Partial plan sketch of 2nd floor deck with spiral staircase]., NYDA.1986.004.00804
        - [Study of 2nd floor plan, showing lay-out]. Also include space computation., NYDA.1986.004.00805
        - [Study of 2nd floor plan showing furniture lay-out]., NYDA.1986.004.00806
        - [Plan of (?) showing stairs]., NYDA.1986.004.00807
        - [Sketch of 4 exterior elevations]., NYDA.1986.004.00808
        - [4 exterior elevations]., NYDA.1986.004.00809
        - [Exterior elevation showing garage door]. Also includes doodle in the lower left corner in ink., NYDA.1986.004.00810
        - [Exterior elevation showing a spiral stair case with its plan]., NYDA.1986.004.00811
        - [2 exterior elevations showing decks and spiral staircase, and a plan of the spiral staircase]., NYDA.1986.004.00812
        - [Sketch of site plan]., NYDA.1986.004.00813
        - [Study of site plan]., NYDA.1986.004.00814
        - [Site plan]., NYDA.1986.004.00815
        - [Block plan showing measurements; block plan keyed to corresponding tables showing area computations]., NYDA.1986.004.00816
        - [Detail section of (?) with notation]., NYDA.1986.004.00817
        - [Study for exterior perspective showing lines of perspective]., NYDA.1986.004.00818
        - [Exterior perspective showing deck with spiral staircase]., NYDA.1986.004.00819
        - [Sketch of detail shown in 1986.004.00817 with light sketch of plan; sketch of presentation board. Presentation is titled "Design for a firesafe conc. house P.P.P. Cement Ass. Arch. Competition"., NYDA.1986.004.00820
      - Papers
        - archival: 1 pamphlet, 3 brochures, 1 clipping. (Box A4, Folder 42-1)
          (Clipping re war housing projects; printed material from the United States Housing Authority and The Regional Plan Association.)
  - Job 43, Alfred DiLiagre
    - [Mr. Alfred De Liagre residence (Woodstock, N.Y.)]
      - Drawings, #.00821-.00967 1917, 1936-1941, 147 sheets: various media; or smaller 76.5 x 103.4 cm.; 30-1/8 x 40-3/4 inches